Hi, this is Matt Baker. For the first
time in over 50 years, humans are going
to the moon. The mission is called
Artemis 2 and it's a really big deal
because although sending humans into
space has become somewhat of a routine
thing, sending them beyond Earth orbit
has not. Let me explain.
This is Earth and this this is what's
called lower Earth orbit. It's basically
everything from about 160 km above the
Earth's surface to 2,000 km above the
Earth's surface. To date, of the 384
human space flights that have been
launched into space, only nine, that's
right, nine have gone beyond lower Earth
orbit. These unique space flights
traveled all the way to the moon, which
as you can see makes for a much farther
trip. The last time anyone traveled this
far was way back in 1972.
That is until the current Artemis
mission, which is on its way right now.
It includes the first-ever woman to make
the trip, the first-ever person of
color, and the first non-American. So,
in order to mark this special occasion,
I decided to launch something of my own,
this brand-new timeline of space
exploration chart, which not only covers
the history of human space flight, but
also the many space probes that have
been sent out to explore the solar
system.
If you want to get a copy of this
brand-new chart, just head over to
usefulcharts.com right now or simply
click the link in the description or
pinned comment. In today's video, I'll
be concentrating mostly on the section
showing missions to the moon, but in
future videos, I'll be covering the
other parts as well. So, keep an eye out
for those.
>> [music]
>> The date October the 4th, 1957 is
generally seen as being the start of the
space age. That's because that's the day
that the Soviet Union launched Sputnik
1, which became the first-ever
human-made object to orbit the Earth. Up
to that point, there had been rockets
that had reached space, the definition
being 100 km above the Earth, but their
payloads had all fallen back down after
just a few minutes, something that's
called a suborbital space flight.
Sputnik 1 was different because it
reached the speed necessary to stay in
space. In other words, to go round and
round the Earth without falling,
something called orbital space flight.
But then, just 1 year later, the Soviet
Union did something even more
remarkable. They launched Luna 1, which
was the first probe to escape Earth's
gravity altogether and to travel all the
way to the moon. It was actually
supposed to hit the moon, meaning crash
into it, but it missed and therefore
ended up being a flyby mission. Luna 2,
launched in October 1958, was the first
probe to actually hit the moon and thus
is the oldest human-made object on the
surface. Now, neither Luna 1 nor Luna 2
had a camera on board, but Luna 3 did,
which allowed humanity to see something
it had never seen before. You see, one
of the interesting things about the moon
is that it is tidally locked to the
Earth, which means that when we look up
at it, we always see the same side. But
when Luna 3 flew by the moon, it took
photos and therefore we got our
first-ever look at the far side of the
moon. So, as you can see, it was the
Soviets who were clearly in the lead at
the beginning of the space race. The US
didn't have its first fully successful
mission to the moon until Ranger 7 in
1964. It purposefully crash-landed on
the moon and sent back the first-ever
high-resolution photos of the surface
before it did so. Now, one thing you
need to know about this chart is that it
doesn't show every single successful
mission. So, for example, after Ranger 7
came Ranger 8 and 9, which also impacted
the moon.
Okay, so the next step was to land on
the moon, not by crashing, but by making
what's called a soft landing. Yet again,
it was the Soviets who were the first to
do this with Luna 9 in February of 1966.
But this time, the US was close behind,
soft-landing Surveyor 1 just a few
months later.
Likewise, the Soviets were also first to
get one of their probes to orbit the
moon, Luna 10 in March of '66. But the
US was once again close behind,
achieving the same thing with Lunar
Orbiter 1 in August. Now, of course, the
real goal was not to just keep sending
robotic spacecrafts to the moon, but to
eventually send one with humans. But in
order to achieve this, humans first had
to conquer lower Earth orbit. So, let's
back up a bit and quickly take a look at
that. When it comes to human space
flight, the Soviets had a program called
Vostok and the US had one called Project
Mercury. Both countries used animals for
test flights, but take note that whereas
the Soviets did test flights with dogs,
the US used monkeys and apes. Again, the
Soviets were initially ahead. So, the
first higher organisms to survive
orbital space flight ended up being two
dogs named Belka and Strelka in 1960
aboard Korabl-Sputnik 2, a prototype for
Vostok. Laika had been sent into orbit
earlier on Sputnik 2, but sadly did not
survive. And even earlier, way back in
1951, Dezik and Tsigan had been sent
into space and had survived, but their
flight had been suborbital, not orbital.
However, with Belka and Strelka's
successful orbital flight, the path was
made clear for a human to fly aboard
Vostok. As you probably know, the first
human to fly to space was a Soviet man
named Yuri Gagarin aboard Vostok 1 in
1961. There were six Vostok flights
altogether and the last one, Vostok 6 in
1963, carried the first woman to fly to
space, Valentina Tereshkova. Meanwhile,
the US was busy with Project Mercury. It
sent Ham the chimpanzee into space just
a few months before Yuri Gagarin and
then the first American, Alan Shepard,
about 1 month after Gagarin. But take
note that these two flights were both
suborbital. The first American to make
an orbital space flight was John Glenn
in 1962.
Next came the Voskhod program in the
Soviet Union and Project Gemini in the
US, both of which featured two-person
spacecrafts. Both programs involved the
first-ever spacewalks by each country
and in addition to this, Gemini in
particular focused on astronauts
learning to do certain maneuvers in
space, such as changing orbit and
docking, things that would be important
for future lunar missions. Okay, so up
to this point, the Soviets had been the
clear front-runners in the space race.
However, starting in the year 1966,
things started to turn in favor of the
US after the Soviets suffered several
major tragedies in a row. The first was
the unexpected death of Sergei Korolev.
You are probably familiar with the name
Wernher von Braun, the former Nazi who
was then recruited by the US, becoming
their chief rocket engineer. Well,
Korolev was basically the Soviets'
Wernher von Braun. So, losing him right
in the middle of the space race was a
major blow. Then in 1967, the next
Soviet spacecraft, the Soyuz, which
could hold up to three crew members,
crash-landed during its very first
mission, killing the pilot. This was
followed by Yuri Gagarin's death in 1968
in a plane crash. And then the failure
of their moon rocket, the N1, in 1969.
The US also suffered a major tragedy in
1966 when astronauts died in a cockpit
fire while testing the new Apollo
spacecraft. But then, things got better
and better. Take note that the Apollo
program box has three columns. This
first one represents flights that stayed
within lower Earth orbit, whereas the
second represents flights to the moon
that did not land, and the third
represents flights to the moon that did
land. Now, although everyone tends to
focus on Apollo 11 as it was the mission
that landed humans on the moon for the
very first time, Apollo 8 was in many
ways even more important. Similar in
scope to the Artemis 2 mission occurring
right now, Apollo 8 saw the first humans
to be launched aboard a Saturn 5 rocket,
which was the US's equivalent of the
Soviet N1. But whereas the N1 failed,
the Saturn 5 succeeded and sent humans
past lower Earth orbit very first time
and onwards towards the vicinity of the
moon. It is estimated that a quarter of
the world's population was watching when
Apollo 8 arrived at the moon on
Christmas Eve 1968, at which time the
astronauts read some verses from Genesis
chapter 1, ending with "We close with
good night. Good luck, a Merry
Christmas, and God bless all of you, all
of you on the good Earth." They also
took this famous photo called Earthrise,
which was the first-ever
color
picture of the Earth taken from the moon
and which has been credited with
launching the modern environmentalist
movement. After Apollo 8, there were two
more test flights and then six actual
moon
and ending with Apollo 17 in 1972. Each
time, two astronauts landed on the moon,
while a third astronaut stayed aboard
the main spacecraft and orbited the
moon. That means to date, only 12 people
have had the privilege of actually
walking on the moon. The final three
missions are notable in that they were
longer, spending about 3 days on the
surface each time. They also made use of
the lunar roving vehicle.
Now, if you look closely, you'll notice
that Apollo 13 is missing from the list
of landing missions. That's because it
was supposed to land on the moon, but
didn't due to an exploded oxygen tank.
The story of that mission and how the
astronauts managed to make it home
safely is told in the Tom Hanks movie
Apollo 13.
Now, while the Soviets did not ever send
any humans to the moon, they did
actually complete several more important
lunar missions. For example, a few
months before Apollo 8, they succeeded
in sending the first-ever life forms to
the moon aboard Zond 5, which included
two tortoises who arrived back to Earth
home safely. During the '70s, the
Soviets also completed several sample
return missions, as well as two missions
involving robotic rovers, Lunokhod 1 and
Lunokhod 2.
But then, following Luna 24 in 1976,
exploration of the moon abruptly
stopped. And for the next 14 years,
there was not a single lunar mission
launched by any country. So, no missions
to the moon during the 1980s. There were
two main reasons for this. First, with
the completion of the Apollo moon
landings, the US had basically won the
space race hands down. So, there was no
longer any pressure to keep things up at
such a fast pace. Second, priorities
switched to perfecting travel within
lower Earth orbit. So, to this end, the
Soviets focused on space stations and
the US on the space shuttle. We'll be
looking at these topics in a future
video.
But for now, since our focus is on the
moon, we are going to jump ahead to the
'90s and early 2000s, which is when
robotic missions to the moon resumed,
albeit quite sporadically at first,
starting with the Hiten orbiter sent by
Japan, making Japan the third country to
successfully send a spacecraft to the
moon. Next came two more orbiters,
Clementine and Lunar Prospector, both
sent by the US. These two are notable in
that they were the first to detect the
presence of ice on the moon near its
poles. And then finally, for this
period, we get the Smart 1 orbiter sent
by the European Space Agency in 2003.
But it was in the year 2007 that lunar
exploration really started to ramp up
with the arrival of China's first
orbiter, Chang'e 1, and Japan's second,
Selene. In fact, ever since 2007, the
moon has been continuously monitored by
at least one orbiting spacecraft,
usually more than one. Take note that
the number shown in the purple line
represents the number of spacecrafts
orbiting the moon during any given year.
So, in 2007, it was two, but in 2008, it
went up to three, because that's when
India launched its first lunar orbiter,
Chandrayaan 1.
Now, Chang'e 1, Selene, and Chandrayaan
1 were not meant to be long-term
orbiters. So, during 2009, all three
were purposefully programmed to crash
into the moon. But before the last one
did so, a new orbiter arrived, the US's
Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter. This one
is actually still orbiting the moon to
this very day and has provided us with
the highest-resolution maps of the moon
to date. Now, I won't go through every
orbiter added since then, but I do want
to point out two recent ones, because
they were both sent by countries who are
relatively new to space exploration.
There's South Korea's Danuri orbiter,
which arrived in 2022, and Pakistan's
iCube-Q
orbiter, which arrived in 2024. China is
planning to send another orbiter this
summer, so once that happens, there will
be a total of 11 spacecrafts orbiting
the moon at the same time, the most
ever. You can see the full list here.
Now, I didn't mention it earlier, but a
lot of these names were chosen due to
their connection to the moon. For
example, Chang'e is the Chinese goddess
of the moon, and Chandra is the Hindu
god of the moon. Yan means vehicle, so
Chandrayaan basically means moon
vehicle.
Let's now move over to this line here,
which lists all of the recent surface
activity on the moon, most notably any
lunar rovers. Up until 2013, only two
countries, the Soviet Union and the
United States, had ever soft-landed a
spacecraft on the moon. Well, with the
landing of Chang'e 3, China became the
third country to do so. That mission
included a rover named Yutu, which means
Jade Rabbit. It operated until 2017.
However, in 2019, Chang'e 4 arrived with
Yutu 2, which is still operating on the
moon to this day. This particular
mission is also notable in that it was
the first mission to land on the far
side of the moon.
Next up, India became the fourth country
to soft-land on the moon when
Chandrayaan 3 successfully did so in
2023. It brought with it the Pragyan
rover. Then, the following year, Japan
became the fifth and most recent country
to soft-land on the moon with the
arrival of SLIM, which stands for Smart
Lander for Investigating Moon. It
brought with it two short-term mini
rovers, LEV-1, which moved by hopping,
and the baseball-sized LEV-2, which
crawled. Now, the Chang'e 7 mission that
I mentioned earlier is going to include
not only an orbiter, but also a lander
with some kind of rover and perhaps a
flying vehicle, the exact details of
which have not yet been released.
Okay, we're now ready to talk about the
Artemis program, which is the first
program in over 50 years to send humans
to the moon. It's named after the Greek
goddess of the moon, who was the twin
sister of Apollo. And its history goes
back to the Constellation program, which
was approved by George W. Bush in 2004,
but then canceled by Obama in 2011.
One thing that came out of that program,
though, was a design for a new
deep-space crew vehicle called Orion.
Thus, when the Artemis program was
approved by the first Trump
administration in 2017, it incorporated
the Orion into its plan, as well as a
new rocket based on the Space Shuttle
program called the Space Launch System,
or SLS. A third component, the service
module, which provides Orion with power
and propulsion, has been designed by the
European Space Agency.
All three of these new pieces of
hardware were tested for the very first
time in November of 2022,
during the uncrewed Artemis 1 mission.
Everything went well, which is why in
2026, we've now moved on to the first
crewed flight, Artemis 2. Now, in
between Artemis 1 and 2, there were two
other related missions of note, both by
private companies. The first by
Intuitive Machines, and the second by
Firefly Aerospace. You see, this time
when humans land on the moon, the plan
is for private companies to land the
necessary supplies and equipment ahead
of time. These two missions tested out
this idea, and as such, they mark the
first time that commercial companies
have soft-landed on the moon. So, as you
can see, in just a little more than a
decade, we've gone from only two
countries to have landed on the moon to
five countries, plus two companies, soon
to be followed by several more.
The other thing that private companies
will be helping out with when it comes
to future Artemis missions is providing
the 21st century version of this, the
all-important lunar lander. Two designs
are currently in the works, one by Elon
Musk's SpaceX and one by Jeff Bezos's
Blue Origin.
Now, originally, the plan was for humans
to land on the moon next year, during
the Artemis 3 mission, but now Artemis 3
is going to be just a crewed test flight
using the new lunar lander, and it will
take place within lower Earth orbit,
which means that Artemis 4, currently
scheduled for 2028, will be the landing
mission. During that mission, the plan
is to have two astronauts land on the
moon, one of which will be the
first-ever woman to do so, and two
astronauts to stay in lunar orbit. Now,
it is possible that that mission could
be delayed, but there is now some
pressure to make sure it happens fairly
soon, because the Chinese have stated
that they hope to land humans on the
moon around 2030. So, yet again, we have
a bit of a space race.
As to what things will look like further
out, it's hard to say. Initially, the
plan was to build a space station around
the moon called Gateway, but rumor has
it that that's likely to get canceled,
and instead, the focus will be on
building a permanent moon base only.
Okay, so that was a look at several of
the most important missions to the moon,
including Artemis 2, which is happening
right now. Once again, if you want to
get a copy of this brand new timeline of
space exploration chart, just head over
to usefulcharts.com
right now. Or simply click the link in
the description or pinned comment.
Thanks for watching.